Preliminary Inventory to the Frank E. (Earl) Mason Papers, 1915-1975
Hoover Institution Archives
Frank E. (Earl) Mason Papers,
1915-1975
XX007
Mason, Frank E., 1893-1979
4 manuscript boxes, 7 envelopes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, journalistic dispatches, and other material, relating to German and Soviet politics and diplomacy in the interwar period, and to Allied military administration of Germany at the end of World War II. Includes a copy of the logbook of the submarine that sank the Lusitania, 1915, and correspondence with Georgii Chicherin and Karl von Wiegand.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
William II, German Emperor, 1859-1941.; Lusitania (Steamship); Denazification.; Prisoners of war.; World politics.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.; Germany.; Germany--History--1945-1955.; Germany--Politics and government--20th century.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations.; Journalists.; Bryant, Louise.; Chicherin, Georgii Vasil'evich, 1872-1936.; Dryander, Ernst H., 1843-1922.; Eisenhower, Milton Stover, 1899-; Strong, Anna Louise.; Von Wiegand, Karl H.; Wilhelm, Crown Prince of the German Empire and of Prussia, 1882-1951.; Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955) Control Council.; Essener Nationalzeitung; Le Petit Journal
Biographical Note
1893 Born, Milwaukee, Wis.
1918 Intelligence officer, 9th Infantry, U.S. Army
Instructor, Army Intelligence School, Langres, France
1919 Chief censor advocate, G.H.Q., Gen. Staff, German occupied area Military observer, Berlin (March-July) Assistant military attaché, American Legation, The Hague; American Embassy, Berlin
1920-1921 Berlin correspondent, International News Service
1921 London manager
1922-1926 Paris manager
1927 New York, business manager
1928ff. General manager and president
1931-1945 Vice-president of NBC
1941-1944 Special assistant to secretary of the Navy
1946 Member of the Food Emergency Mission
Container List
- Lusitania story - copies of the log book of the U-20, 1915 April 30-May 13, including clippings, etc. (Box 1.)
- Report on a trip to Moscow in 1930 June, by Otto Tolischus, Berlin correspondent of International News Service, to Barry Farris, General News Manager, International News Service
- Telegrams from Tchitcherin to Frank Earl Mason on Russian-Polish relations, 1920, etc.
- Miscellany: correspondence between Frank Earl Mason and Dr. Milton S. Eisenhower, 1947; report of Baron Rochus Freiherr von Rheinbaben about his experiences in American prison camps in France, 1918-1919; and clipping of an article about Herbert Hoover by Kaarlo Jarvi from an American-Finnish newspaper, 1954 August
- Typed extracts from Essener Nationalzeitung, 1932 March-1947 March
- Forty-six letters from Karl von Wiegand, American newspaper correspondent (1914 to the mid-1950s) to "Ellen" (Mrs. Frank Earl Mason,) and Frank Earl Mason, 1931-1934, 1954-1958
- Headquarters U.S. Group Control Council (Germany) Public Relations Service, "Action of the Control Council, 1945 September 10," 1945 September 11, re transport (neg. and posit.)
- Reminiscences of the German Kaiser's (Wilhelm II) Imperial Pastor, Dr. von Dryander, about the Kaiser's student days at the University of Bonn, 1919.m Also statement by Dr. von Dryander about the intellectual and religious development in Germany's future, 1920 October (3 items, including translations)
- Mimeographed order (18 pages) of the U.S. Army High Command, Vienna, 1945 August 3, giving instructions to the U.S. Army of Occupation authorities on arrest, detention and punishment of mandatory as well as optional classifications of Nazis
- Historical issue of Le Petit Journal, 1918 October 29, announcing the collapse of U.S. enemy forces, Austro-Hungary's proposal for surrender and a separate peace, and Germany's request for armistice conditions from President Woodrow Wilson
- Six volumes of Berlin correspondent Frank Earl Mason's International News Service dispatches, 1919 October-1921 September. Included are interview and press articles by Moscow correspondents Louise Bryant and Anna Louise Strong (Box 2-3.)
- Printed invitations, tickets, and memorabilia, 1919-1935, relating to party functions of the Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei (Box 3.)
- Das braune Haus, by A. Dresler (pamphlet)
- Frank Earl Mason's correspondence file on the plot of four American newspaper people against General Patton, and incident, which occurred in 1945 September at 3rd Army Headquarters in Bad Tölz, Bavaria, Germany (1 folder)
- Copy of a letter from Hanz Walz, Stuttgart, Germany, 1950 April 19, concerning plot to overthrow Hitler, and activities of former mayor Goerdeler of Leipzig, Germany. Included is a list of meditations by Brig. Gen. Carter Clarke on the 34th anniversary of Pearl Harbor, 1975
- Copy (neg.) of press releases, 1945, regarding the agreement to place the American line of communication under Russian control and supervision
- Letter to John Toland, author of a projected book on the last hundred days of World War I, concerning Frank Earl Mason's service in the 9th Infantry as Intelligence officer in France in 1918 (Box 4.)
- Two pamphlets by John T. Flynn
  - The Thought Police: An Episode in Radical Bigotry, 1946 (2 copies)
  - Smear Terror, 1947
- German Union for League of Nations, "Conditions of Peace of the Allied and Associated Powers"; complete reproduction of the official text (Berlin, Germany, H. R. Engelman, 1919)
- Five original Japanese propaganda leaflets, distributed by air to American troops on the Pacific Islands in 1943
- Letter (2 pages) by Col. Albert L. Conger, 1921 April 10, to Captain Frank Earl Mason, regarding the Viviani (French leader) Mission to the United States
- Interview, entitled "Hitler's Interpreter, Dr. Paul Schmidt, in Conversation with Donald McLachlan" (The Listener, vol. 83, no. 2142, issued by the British Broadcasting Company)